A Register of the Vasilii Ivanovich Alekseev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vasilii Ivanovich Alekseev Papers
1954-1967
2008C80
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
These papers reflect the writings and research interests of Vasilii Ivanovich Alekseev, a historian, writer, and professor in emigration. Among his writings are works related to the Russian Orthodox Church in the Soviet Union under the German occupation.
Alekseev, Vasilii Ivanovich
Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Original Materials
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1906 October 6 Born, Vladimir, Russia
1930 Graduated, Moscow State University Arrested and sentenced to five years in prison camp
1934 Released from prison camp
1941 Drafted
1942 POW camp, Germany
1951 Arrived in the United States
1952 Author, Nevidimaia Rossiia
1954 Author, Rossiia soldatskaia
1955-1975 Taught Russian history, University of Minnesota
1955 Author, The foreign policy of the Moscow Patriarchate, 1939-1953: materials for the history of the Russian Orthodox Church in the U.S.S.R.
1962 Author, The two Russian revolutions of 1917
1967 Defended Ph.D. dissertation, University of Minnesota
1976 Author, The great revival: the Russian Church under German occupation
1990 Author, Rol' tserkvi v sozdanii russkoi gosudarstva: period ot nashestviia tatar do Ivana III
2002 October 8 Died, Minneapolis, MN
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers reflect the writings and research interests of Vasilii Ivanovich Alekseev, a historian, writer, and professor in emigration. Among his writings are works related to the Russian Orthodox Church in the Soviet Union under the German occupation. The Speeches and writings and Subject file include notes and copied archival documents, relating to Alekseev's dissertation, and research interests.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: Correspondence, Speeches and writings, and Subject file
Related Material
V. I Alekseev Papers, T.C. Anderson library, University of Minnesota
Biography
Vasilii Ivanovich Alekseev was born in Vladimir, Russia, on October 6, 1906. He graduated from Moscow University in 1930 and fell victim to the repressions of the Soviet government the same year, being arrested and sentenced to five years of labor in a prison camp. In 1941 he was drafted; by 1942 he was in a German POW camp. Fleeing repatriation to the Soviet Union, Alekseev managed to immigrate to the United States, where he arrived in 1951.
In the United States, Alekseev begins his career as writer and historian, publishing numerous books on Russian history, such as Nevidimaia Rossiia, Rossiia soldatskaia, The Foreign Policy of the Moscow Patriarchate, 1939–1945, The Two Russian Revolutions of 1917, The Great Revival: the Russian Church under German Occupation, and Rol’ Tserkvi v sozdanii russkogo gosudarstva.
Alekseev taught Russian history at the University of Minnesota from 1955 to1975 and defended his Ph.D. dissertation at the same institution in 1967.
He died on October 8, 2002, in Minneapolis, MN.
Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'--History.; Soviet Union--History--German occupation, 1941-1944.; Soviet Union--History.
- Correspondence, 1954-1958 and undated. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Leontii, Bishop, 1954 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Shchukin, Sergei, Reverend, undated (Folder 1: 2)
  - Vissarion (Pui), Metropolitan, 1958. (Folder 1: 3)
    Includes "L'Archeveque Roumain Vissarion en Transnistrie (Ucraine) en 1943," undated typescript
- Speeches and writings, 1967 and undated.
  Articles, monographs, and notes, arranged chronologically by title
  - Notes, undated
    - General (Folder 1: 4)
    - Interviews (Folder 1: 5)
    - Notebook (Folder 1: 6)
    - German legislation in regards to the Russian Orthodox Church, 1941-1944 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Ministry for Eastern Territories, Third Reich (Folder 1: 8)
    - Records of the Security police of the Third Reich (Folder 1: 9)
    - Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'--History--Belarus (Folder 1: 10)
    - Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'--History--Poland (Folder 1: 11)
    - Smolensk archives (Folder 1: 12)
    - Ukrainian Orthodox Church, biographical data on hierarchs (Folder 1: 13)
    - World War, 1939-1945, Camp Plattling, Germany (Folder 1: 14)
    - Zhurnal moskovskoi patriarkhii (Folder 1: 15)
  - "Moskovskaia patriarkhiia, religioznyi pod"em v Rossii i sovetskaia propaganda,", undated. (Folder 1: 16)
    Typescript
  - "Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov' na okkupirovannoi nemtsami territorii,", undated. (Folder 1: 17)
  - "Smert' ekzarkha Sergiia Voskresenskogo i vybory moskovskogo patriarkha v svete sekretnykh nemetskikh dokumentov,", undated. (Folder 1: 18)
    Typescript, includes notes
  - "The Russian Orthodox Church under German occupation,", 1967.
    - Bibliography (Folder 1: 19)
    - Typescript. (Folder 1: 20-21)
      Includes related notes
- Subject file, undated. (Box 2-4)
  Includes photocopies from various archives, as well as related notes and citations from published works. Not filmed, originals retained by Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary.
  - Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'--History
  - Soviet Union--History
  - Soviet Union--History--German occupation, 1941-1944.
    Includes materials on the Russian Orthodox Church in Belarus, and the Ukraine